Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series XX: Namibia: The Last Colony, 1989-1990; 479732
  - Independence of Namibia, 1990; 467224 (Box 43, Cassette ref829, Box 97, Dvd ref829)
    This video features footage recorded live at the swearing-in ceremony of the first Namibian president Sam Nujoma in 1990. The footage largely features crowds and dignitaries arriving at Windhoek Stadium (later called Independence Stadium) in Windhoek, Namibia. The footage appears to be live coverage recorded by NBC News. The swearing in ceremony features speeches by United Nations Secretary General Javier Pèrez de Cuèllar and South African President Frederik Willem de Klerk. Nujoma is sworn-in as Namibia's first president by de Cuèllar and makes a brief speech at the end of the video.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:00:28.
- Series XXI: The National Ballet of Cuba in Argentina, 1984; 479669
  In the 21-minute documentary The National Ballet of Cuba in Argentina Alicia Alonso, renowned ballerina, returns to Buenos Aires after a 20-year absence to perform in the Colon Theater in Luna Park. Nobel Prize-winner Perez Esquivel and others give their impressions and members of the National Ballet of Cuba describe their experiences. This series contains one video recording associated with this film. It is unclear whether it is a complete copy of the documentary or uncut footage.
  - "Ballet Nacional Cuba 3rd Part in Buenos Aires Master", circa 1984; 479670 (Box 58, Cassette ref1327)
- Series XXII: Operation Peter Pan: Flying Back to Cuba, 1979-2013; 479663
  In 1960, rumors circulated Cuba that the new revolutionary government planned to suspend parental authority and enroll the children in military schools or send them to Russia for Communist indoctrination. In the wake of the rumors, Cuban parents sent as many as 14,000 unaccompanied children on flights out of Cuba between 1960 and 1962. The United States government facilitated this mass exodus of Cuban children, which became popularly known as Operation Peter Pan, through a clandestine program that waived the children's visa requirements and provided several million dollars to the Miami Catholic Welfare Bureau to care for the children. Many parents expected to be reunited with their children after what they believed would be the swift fall communist government. Following the Bay of Pigs invasions in 1962, however, US-Cuba relations deteriorated, and permanently separated many parents and children. Some children were able to connect with family members in the United States, but approximately 7000 were moved into long-term orphanages or foster care.
  Estela Bravo's documentary Operation Peter Pan: Flying Back to Cuba about the experience of these children was selected as Best Documentary Feature at the 2011 Havana Film Festival in New York. It also won First Prize at the Festival Internacional de Cine Politico, Buenos Aires; Best Documentary at the 7th Human Rights International Festival in Bolivia; and the Coral Award at the International Festival of New Latin American Cinema.
  This 57-minute documentary Operation Peter Pan (Operación Peter Pan) was released in 2011 and tells the story of the mass migration of Cuban minors to the United States. It uses footage from the National Archives and features interviews with individuals who traveled to the United States in Operation Peter Pan. The film primarily centers on a group of five who traveled back to Cuba for the first time after almost fifty years. Estela Bravo follows them as they explore their past and help bridge the emotional and political divides between the United States and Cuba.
  This series contains footage of interviews with select individuals featured in the documentary, a selection of background footage, and a copy of the book Operation Peter Pan based on the documentary.
  - Operación Peter Pan: Book Based on the Documentary by Estela Bravo, 2013; 592988 (Box 72, Folder 25)
  - Fonseca, L.: Interview about Operation Peter Pan and Father Brian O. Walsh, undated; 467317 (Box 40, Cassette ref736, Box 97, Dvd ref736)
    The video begins with black and white footage of an interview with two men. This portion is barely audible and audio and video quality is poor throughout. The majority of the video focuses on footage of father Brian O. Walsh who facilitated the transportation of Cuban children to the United States during Operation Peter Pan. A young man watches the footage and describes what his experience as one of the Peter Pan children and his memories of his life in the United States. He discusses traveling to the U.S. at the age of 12 and later deciding to return to Cuba. He explains that he eventually returned to Cuba in 1971, but that the process was difficult.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:49.
  - Mendieta, Ana: Interview also "Juan Monge and Zenon", circa 2010; cuid391; 467323 (Box 40, Cassette ref730, Box 95, Dvd ref730)
    Ana Mendieta (1948 – 1985) was a Cuban American performance artist, sculptor, painter and video artist. Born in Havana, Mendieta and her sister were sent to the United States as a part of Operation Peter Pan in 1961. Their first weeks were spent in refugee camps before moving to several institutions and foster homes in Iowa. They were eventually reunited with their mother in 1966 and their father in 1979.
  - Mendieta, Ana: Interview "and Zenon and Monge", circa 2010; cuid392; 467320 (Box 40, Cassette ref733, Box 95, Dvd ref733)
  - Walsh, Bryan O.: Interview, undated; cuid393; 467309 (Box 40, Cassette ref744)
    Monsignor Bryan O. Walsh (1930-2001) was born in Ireland, moved to the United States and was ordained for the Diocese of St. Augustine, Florida in 1954. He directed the Cuban Children's Program, which brought 14,000 unaccompanied children from Cuba to the United States.
  - Walsh, Bryan O.: Interview, circa 1979; cuid394; 467312 (Box 40, Cassette ref741, Box 97, Dvd ref741)
    This video features and interview with Father Bryan O. Walsh. Walsh begins by discussing the children currently in the care of his Catholic organization in Miami. At the time of the interview Walsh explained that he was caring for 25 children between the ages of 14 and 18. He describes the motivation of many Cuban parents who decided to send their children to the United States in the early 1960s, explaining that many feared their children would be sent to Russia for communist indoctrination. He also discusses his organization's role in clandestine efforts to send Cuban children the US, and explains that parents expected Castro would be overthrown and their children would quickly return. He later discusses children who had a difficult time adjusting to life in the US, and the Miami-based youth organization the Antonio Maceo Brigade, which was outspoken in its support of the Cuban government.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:59.
  - Interview with girl (Nina), Casa de las Americas, 1979; cuid395; 467319 (Box 40, Cassette ref734)
  - "Early interview with Emilio Cueto", undated; 467516 (Box 23, Cassette ref537)
    Emilio Cueto is a lawyer, author, pianist, and collector of Cuban cultural artifacts. Born in Cuba, he came to the United States as one of the Operation Peter Pan children.
  - "Peter Pan", 467421 (Box 32, Cassette ref632)
  - "Camp Photos, Walsh", undated; 467314 (Box 40, Cassette ref739)
  - "Part of 'Lost Apple'", undated; 467311 (Box 40, Cassette ref742)
  - "Walsh, Lost Apple, Peter Pan", undated; 467252 (Box 39, Cassette ref801)
- Series XXIII: Returning to Chile, 1984-1986; 479218
  In the 1970s several thousand Chilean citizens fled their country to escape the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. Most of the exiles were either supporters of former president Salvador Allende or activists on the political left who feared abuse under the new government. Exiles were barred from returning for many years, but by 1984 the Chilean government agreed to grant most of the exiles permission to return home. This opening was spurred by international pressure and a domestic campaign to abolish restrictions on exiles.
  Returning to Chile, which documents the return of Chilean political exiles, won a 1986 Silver Toucan Award at the Rio de Janiero International Film Festival.
  Estela Bravo's 1986 documentary Returning to Chile tells the story of Chileans exiles who returned to the country in the mid-1980s. This documentary explores the experience of youth who returned to Chile without their parents after living in exile for many years. Several of the youths featured in the documentary discuss their difficulty adjusting to life in Chile and struggles with identity. A portion of the film focuses on Carlos Godoy Echegoyen, a twenty-three-year-old Socialist who died under torture in a police station in the port of Quintero in February 1985, shortly after returning from exile. Bravo interviews his mother and his sister. It also features scenes in a cemetery at Godoy's grave and the graves of others, including Victor Jara, and Salvador Allende. The film also tells the story of three children from one family whose parents were taken and who must fend for themselves.
  Videos in this series include full-length copies of the documentary with subtitles in English as well as raw footage and interviews. Footage features cemetery scenes, discussions about Carlos Godoy, Chilean religious and social welfare groups, speeches by Pinochet, and other background scenes.
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; 593065; 1 Reels (Reel ref2162_01, Reel ref2162_02)
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; 2013.014; 593072 (Reel ref2167)
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; cuid791; 479645 (Box 57, Cassette ref1302, Box 96, Dvd ref1302)
    This video contains a full version of short documentary Returning to Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:29:24.
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; 479683 (Box 61, Cassette ref1340)
    This is most likely a full-length version of the film Returning to Chile. This film is in Spanish.
  - Returning to Chile, "Cassette #24 DV #9 Final Viejo, Spanish", circa 1984-1986; 479220 (Box 45, Cassette ref968)
  - Returning to Chile "English subtitles", circa 1984-1986; 467219 (Box 43, Cassette ref834, Box 97, Dvd ref834)
    This video features a complete version of the documentary Returning to Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:29:56.
  - Returning to Chile, English, circa 1984-1986; 479223 (Box 45, Cassette ref969)
  - "Pinochet Speech", circa 1984-1986; 479576 (Box 53, Cassette ref1234, Box 98, Dvd ref1234)
    This video features a speech by Augusto Pinochet delivered on September 11, the anniversary of the military coup in which he seized power in Chile. In his speech, Pinochet contends that Chile must continue to fight against communism and Marxism. He discusses the history of communism and argues that Chile must stay vigilant because the goal of communism is to take over the world. He contends that his government is protecting democracy, and argues that if critics understood the threat that Chile faced they would know that his actions were correct. The second half of this video features footage of a Cuban dramatic television program filmed by Estela Bravo.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:11.
  - Godoy, Carlos (CH13), circa 1985-1986; 479569 (Box 65, Cassette ref1227)
  - Mother of Carlos Godoy: Interview / Protection of Youth Damaged by State of Emergency (PIDEE) (CH14), circa 1985-1986; 479570 (Box 53, Cassette ref1228, Box 98, Dvd ref1228)
    This video begins with an interview with the mother of assassinated political activist Carlos Godoy. Godoy's mother begins by discussing the youth movement in Chile and the reasons Chilean youth have expressed such strong resistance to the Pinochet government. At the time of the interview, which was filmed sometime around 1985, she explains that the children have lived under Pinochet for 12 years and many remember their family members disappearing or going into exile, and cannot see a future for themselves under the current government. She expresses her hope in the community and her faith that the government will eventually change. The video then focuses on news reports and photos of Carols Godoy and his murder. At minute 17:55 the videos changes to an interview with the executive secretary of the foundation Protection of Youth Damaged by State of Emergency (PIDEE), which helped children whose parents had been harmed, detained, or disappeared by the government. She describes the foundation, its goals, and the kind of support it provides to the children whose families were targeted for political reasons.
  - Godoy, Carlos: Interview with Sister (CH18), circa 1985-1986; 479595 (Box 54, Cassette ref1253, Box 98, Dvd ref1253)
    This video features an interview with the sister and mother of murdered Chilean political prisoner Carlos Godoy. The video begins with shots of still images of Godoy, and the interview with his mother and sister begin around minute 3:35. His sister begins by talking about a dove necklace she was wearing, which was made by political prisoners in Santiago. She then discusses how her family moved to Cuba in 1973 following the coup of Augusto Pinochet, and their decision to return to Chile. She describes learning about her brother's death and how the news affected her. She also discusses her hopes of becoming a lawyer or journalist in the future, and her desire to find work that will serve the community.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:32.
  - "Godoy and Sister", circa 1984-1986; 479584 (Box 53, Cassette ref1242)
  - "Cemeteries, Godoy, Desolvencias", 1986; 479598 (Box 54, Cassette ref1256)
  - "Cemetery (CH19)", 1986; 479572 (Box 65, Cassette ref1230)
  - "Cemetery (CH20)", 1986; 467221 (Box 43, Cassette ref832, Box 97, Dvd ref832)
    This video features footage of families in a cemetery in Chile visiting the graves of their loved ones who had been killed by the Central Nacional de Informaciones (CNI), the Chilean military police. At the beginning of the video police can be see chasing demonstrators outside of the cemetery. The video then features an interview with the mother of Carlos Godoy at his grave. Godoy's mother talks about her son, and his murder, and describes him as emblematic of many Chilean youth. After the interview with Godoy's mother, a man speaks about the memory of Godoy and the importance of continued resistance against Augusto Pinochet in Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:48.
  - "3 Children, Home, Singing (CH22)", circa 1984-1986; 479585 (Box 53, Cassette ref1243)
  - "Original, 3 Children, Brother", circa 1984-1986; 479591 (Box 54, Cassette ref1249)
  - "3rd Part, Children, School", circa 1984-1986; 479589 (Box 54, Cassette ref1247)
  - "3 Children, Street action, Foundation for Social Aid of the Christian Churches (FASIC) ", circa 1984-1986; 479565 (Box 65, Cassette ref1223)
  - "FASIC, Venceremos (CH23)", circa 1984-1986; 479573 (Box 65, Cassette ref1231)
  - "FASIC, Young People (CH25)", circa 1984-1986; 479586 (Box 53, Cassette ref1244)
  - "FASIC, Young People (CH26)", circa 1984-1986; 479587 (Box 53, Cassette ref1245)
  - "FASIC, Young People", circa 1984-1986; 479596 (Box 54, Cassette ref1254, Box 98, Dvd ref1254)
    This video features interviews with 4 young Chilean women who returned to Chile after living abroad for many years. The young women describe how life in Chile are different from their lives abroad in France and Canada. Recorded sometime around 1985, the young women discuss how the political culture has changed since the overthrow of president Salvador Allende. One discusses why her family moved to Canada, and her memories of Chile before they left. They also discuss the reasons they decided to return to Chile, and briefly discuss their involvement in youth activist movements.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:28.
  - "PIDEE Cuban Young People", circa 1984-1986; 479597 (Box 54, Cassette ref1255)
    Protection of Youth Damaged by State of Emergency (PIDEE) is an organization founded in 1979 and dedicated to healing childhoods shattered by political repression in Chile.
  - "Casa Hogar, PIDEE, Jovenes, Casa Linda", circa 1984-1986; 479594 (Box 54, Cassette ref1252)
  - "Peace, Young People (CH15)", circa 1984-1986; 479571 (Box 65, Cassette ref1229)
  - "Moneda", circa 1984-1986; 479575 (Box 65, Cassette ref1233)
    Palacio de La Moneda is the Chilean presidential palace. Salvador Allende is believed to have committed suicide at La Moneda just prior to its capture by the troops of General Augusto Pinochet (Sep 11,1973).
  - "Mural, Young Children, Church (CH28)", circa 1984-1986; 479574 (Box 65, Cassette ref1232)
  - "Mexican Families (CH8)", circa 1984-1986; 479581 (Box 53, Cassette ref1239)
  - Returning to Chile "Festivales", circa 1984-1986; 479686 (Box 59, Cassette ref1343)
  - Chile - Pinochet (CH5), circa 1984-1986; 479593 (Box 54, Cassette ref1251)
  - Chile (CH3), circa 1984-1986; 479592 (Box 54, Cassette ref1250)
  - "Pinochet", circa 1984-1986; 479588 (Box 53, Cassette ref1246)
  - "Premio Ret a Chile Casa", circa 1984-1986; 467222 (Box 43, Cassette ref831)
  - Returning to Chile: Video Clips, undated; TW_TAM_616_ER_11 (Box Electronic Records, Folder TW_TAM_616_ER_11)
  - "Retornando a Chile", circa 1984-1986; 467373 (Box 31, Cassette ref680)
- Series XXIV: Silvio and Pablo in Argentina, 1984; 479609
  The documentary Silvio and Pablo in Argentina (1984) shows footage from a concert held in Argentina in 1984 following the country's transition from a military dictatorship to democracy. Silvio Rodriguez and Pablo Milanes, two of Cuba's most popular composer-singer-musicians, organized the concert, which featured some of the best Argentine folk musicians at that time. The documentary shows the enthusiastic response of the Argentine people, as the musicians perform songs that had previously been prohibited in Argentina. This series contains footage of Rodriguez and Milanes in Argentina, as well as some footage of the performers at a concert in the Bronx.
  - Silvio and Pablo Tape 1, 1979-1984; 479691 (Box 66, Cassette ref1348)
    This video does not contain footage from the Bravo documentary, but rather footage of the concert itself.
  - Silvio and Pablo Tape 2, 1984; 479690 (Box 66, Cassette ref1347)
  - Silvio and Pablo footage, circa 1984; 468044 (Box 89, Cassette ref9, Box 75, Dvd ref9)
    This tape contains concert footage for first 4.5 minutes. It is followed by unrelated strike footage and an interview with no sound.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:07:50.
  - Footage: Silvio and Pablo in Argentina, 1984; 479610 (Box 54, Cassette ref1268)
  - Silvio and Pablo Concert at Hostos Community College (Bronx NY), 1979 February 15; cuid396; 479704 (Box 66, Cassette ref1357, Box 96, Dvd ref1357)
    The first 17:30 minutes of this video feature footage of a concert with Cuban folk singers Silvio Rodriguez and Pablo Milanes at Hostos Community College in the Bronx, NY. At minute 17:30 video changes to footage of men in a barbershop.
  - Pablo Milanes at the Karl Marx Theater, undated; 467408 (Box 93, Cassette ref645, Box 82, Dvd ref645)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:07:00.
  - "Silvio Pablo Argentina", 1984; cuid397; 467407 (Box 93, Cassette ref646, Box 83, Dvd ref646)
- Series XXV: Those Who Left, 1980-1981; 479242
  Those Who Left (Los Que Se Fueron) is a 58-minute documentary released in 1980 about Cubans who left their country after the 1959 revolution to live in the United States. In the documentary, Estela Bravo sheds light on major events in the history of US-Cuba relations including Operation Peter Pan and the Mariel Boatlift. The documentary also features interviews with Cuban Americans in favor of normalizing relations between the United States and Cuba, and others who support the overthrow of the communist government in Cuba. This series contains interviews with individuals featured in the documentary, footage of immigration workers, and incomplete portions of the documentary, and an early version of the film, which was originally called El Dialogo.
  - Those Who Left, 1980; 2016.025; 593077 (Reel ref2173)
  - Casal, Lourdes: Interview (also other footage), circa 1980; 467281 (Box 5, Cassette ref772, Box 83, Dvd ref772)
    Lourdes Casal (1938-1981) was a Cuban poet, sociologist, and activist. She participated in anti-Batista activities in college, but later left Cuba following the revolution. She moved to New York City in 1962, where she attended the New School and received a PhD in Social Psychology. In 1969 she founded the Institute of Cuban Studies. She later returned to Cuba on a number of occasions. On a trip to Cuba in 1979, her health deteriorated and she decided to stay, dying there in 1981.
    The footage begins with Estela Bravo speaking with several people, then some scenes of group dancing, followed at about 00:01:20, by an interview with Lourdes Casal that lasts for about 17 minutes. At the end is a brief black and white clip with Spanish narration at what appears to be an old building with commemorative signs.
  - Casal, Lourdes: Interview (brief), circa 1980; 467280 (Box 5, Cassette ref773, Box 83, Dvd ref773)
    This brief footage includes about four minutes of an interview with Lourdes Casal. The rest is footage of a march with Estela Bravo speaking to participants. The quality of this footage is poor but it is viewable.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:09:00.
  - Casal, Lourdes: Event (with additional footage), 1980; 467276 (Box 5, Cassette ref777, Box 83, Dvd ref777)
    The first portion of the tape appears to be the ending of an event honoring Lourdes Casal. The event features a speech about Casal, which is followed by long applause.
    The remainder of the footage is of Estela Bravo and seven young people who represent a group who left Cuba but returned as volunteers for construction projects. Bravo asks a few questions, but mostly the volunteers speak. The sound and image quality are poor, but the footage is viewable.
  - Casal, Lourdes, circa 1980; cuid398; 479696 (Box 59, Cassette ref1353, Box 96, Dvd ref1353)
    This video contains a recording of television program about poet Lourdes Casal created by Los Servicios Informativos de la Televisión Cubana. The program features an interview with Casal about the ways in which her life in Cuban and the United States shaped her politics and her writing career. The program also features footage of her funeral in 1981, and brief interview with mourners talking about her significance as a poet and voice of the people. It includes footage of the event in which she was posthumously awarded the Casa De Las Americas Prize in 1981.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:24:20
  - "Catholic Center", 1980; 479706 (Box 60, Cassette ref1359)
  - Cubans in New York: One Year Later, 1981 April-May; 479697 (Box 60, Cassette ref1354, Box 98, Dvd ref1354)
    This video features a complete version of the television program Cubanos en Nueva York: Un Año Después (Cubans in New York: One Year Later). The program was produced for Cuban television by Estela Bravo and contains follow-up interviews with Cubans featured in her documentary Los Que Se Fueron (Those Who Left). Video and audio quality of this recording are very poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:30.
  - "Dialogo R1 Those Who Left", circa 1980; 479627 (Box 55, Cassette ref1285)
  - "El Dialogo Early Version of Those Who Left", circa 1980; 479626 (Box 55, Cassette ref1284)
  - "Escoria" of Union City Interviews, undated; 479662 (Box 58, Cassette ref1319, Box 98, Dvd ref1319)